export const GEOGRAPHYA2017 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. The scale of the map in Representative Fraction (RF) is",
A: "1:25,000.",
B: "1:50,000.",
C: "1:150,000.",
D: "1:250,000.",
answer: "B. 1:50,000.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. The crow fly distance from Doba to Sasi is approximately",
A: "7.5 km.",
B: "6.0km.",
C: "5.5 km.",
D: "4.5 km.",
answer: "C. 5.5 km.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. What is the direction of IREWA from Oki?",
A: "North east",
B: "North",
C: "South",
D: "South east",
answer: "D. South east",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. The symbol ▲ 950 to the north — east of IREWA is",
A: "Bench mark.",
B: "Spot height.",
C: "Beacon.",
D: "Trigonometrical station.",
answer: "D. Trigonometrical station.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. The feature marked H on the map can best be described as a",
A: "Plateau.",
B: "Conical hill.",
C: "Scarp.",
D: "Ridge.",
answer: "B. Conical hill.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. Which of the following settlement is located at the highest altitude?",
A: "Doba",
B: "Duba",
C: "Sasi",
D: "Oki",
answer: "D. Oki",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. The most likely occupation of the people of Oki is",
A: "Fishing.",
B: "Mining.",
C: "Farming.",
D: "Lumbering.",
answer: "C. Farming.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. Which of the following best explains the growth of IREWA?",
A: "Nodal town",
B: "Centre of plantation agriculture",
C: "Good climate",
D: "Industrial town",
answer: "A. Nodal town",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. The most probable reason for the construction of road from IREWA through Sasi to the plantation is",
A: "Because a large percentage of the population lives in Sasi.",
B: "To provide a means of transporting fish from Sasi to IREWA.",
C: "To carry the farmers from Sasi to IREWA.",
D: "To evacuate thrm products from the plantation to the market at IREWA.",
answer: "D. To evacuate their products from the plantation to the market at IREWA.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. Which of the following towns may not be visible from the feature marked H?",
A: "Sasi",
B: "Doba",
C: "Duba",
D: "Oki",
answer: "D. Oki",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. Which of the following methods of representing statistical data would be most suitable for showing annual production of rice for a country on a month to month basis?",
A: "Line graph",
B: "Pie chart",
C: "Bar graph",
D: "Flow chart",
answer: "C. Bar graph",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. Which of the following types of bar graphs shows increases and decreases compared with a given average?",
A: "Divided bar graph",
B: "Group bar graph",
C: "Divergent bar graph",
D: "Percentage bar graph",
answer: "C. Divergent bar graph",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. Simple bar graphs can most suitably be used to represent all the following except",
A: "Values of a country’s export and imports.",
B: "Distribution of population in a country.",
C: "Month by month rainfall records of a town.",
D: "Values of various foodstuffs produced in a country.",
answer: "B. Distribution of population in a country.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. The temperature of the environment changes with",
A: "Erosion.",
B: "Altitude.",
C: "Mass wasting.",
D: "Longitude.",
answer: "B. Altitude.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. The degree of longitude through which the Earth spins with iii three hours is",
A: "15°.",
B: "30°",
C: "45°.",
D: "60°.",
answer: "C. 45°.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. An example of physical weathering process is",
A: "Carbonation",
B: "Exfoliation.",
C: "Hydration.",
D: "Hydrolysis.",
answer: "B. Exfoliation.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. Which of the following rocks is sedimentary?",
A: "Coal",
B: "Gneiss",
C: "Granite",
D: "Marble",
answer: "A. Coal",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. Granitic rocks contain",
A: "Silica and aluminium.",
B: "Silica and iron",
C: "Magnesium and copper.",
D: "Copper and bauxite.",
answer: "A. Silica and aluminium.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. Chemical weathering can take place most effectively when the conditions are",
A: "Cold and dry.",
B: "Hot and wet.",
C: "Cold and wet.",
D: "Hot and dry.",
answer: "C. Cold and wet.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. The temperature at the foot of a mountain is 20°C. If the mountain is 6000 metres above sea level, what will be the approximate temperature at the top of the mountain?",
A: "-19.0°C",
B: "-16.0°C",
C: "14.0°C",
D: "19.0°C",
answer: "A. -19.0°C",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. The planet which revolves around the sun in a clockwise direction is",
A: "Jupiter.",
B: "Mars.",
C: "Saturn.",
D: "Uranus.",
answer: "D. Uranus.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. Under the Greek system of climatic classification, the world is divided into",
A: "Hot, temperate and dry zones.",
B: "Torrid, equatorial and dry zones.",
C: "Temperate, frigid and dry zones.",
D: "Torrid, temperate and frigid zones.",
answer: "D. Torrid, temperate and frigid zones.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. “It is a pinnacle of calcium that grows, from the floor of limestone cave”. This is a description of",
A: "Clint",
B: "Stalagmite",
C: "Stalactite",
D: "Stump",
answer: "C. Stalactite",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. What is the shape of the Earth?",
A: "Geoid",
B: "Eclipse",
C: "Round",
D: "Cuboid",
answer: "A. Geoid",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. Which of the following processes is associated with ejection of magma and other related materials from deep below the Earth’s surface?",
A: "Folding",
B: "Sedimentation",
C: "Metamorphism",
D: "Vulcanicity",
answer: "D. Vulcanicity",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. Which of the following features is of volcanic origin?",
A: "Sill",
B: "Zeugen",
C: "Loess",
D: "Gorge",
answer: "A. Sill",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. The steep-sided flat-floored valley in hot deserts through which occasional flash floods flow is known as",
A: "Bajada.",
B: "Headland.",
C: "Playa.",
D: "Wadi.",
answer: "D. Wadi.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. Rocks in the inner core of the Earth are rich in",
A: "Iron and nickel.",
B: "Nickel and magnes i tim.",
C: "Lead and iron.",
D: "Nickel and lead.",
answer: "A. Iron and nickel.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. Which of the following conditions occur during equinox?",
A: "The Tropic of Cancer experience longer clay than the Tropic of Capricorn.",
B: "All places across the globe experience equal lengths of day and night,",
C: "The length of day at the Equator is shorter than the Tropic of’ cancer.",
D: "The moon is star—shaped all through the night and all over the world.",
answer: "B. All places across the globe experience equal lengths of day and night,",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. The sea water thrown up the beaches by the breaking waves is called",
A: "Backwash.",
B: "Undertow.",
C: "Swash.",
D: "Shore.",
answer: "C. Swash.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. Which type of rainliill occurs when two air masses of ci ifferent temperatLires and other physical proper ies meet?",
A: "Orographic",
B: "Relief",
C: "Cyclonic",
D: "Convectional",
answer: "D. Convectional",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. Two towns X and V are situated on the Equator. If town X is on the Greenwich Meridian and town V is on longitude 45°E, what will be the time of town Y, if the time at town X is 4.00 pm?",
A: "3.00 pm",
B: "5.00 pm",
C: "6.00 pm",
D: "7.00 pm",
answer: "D. 7.00 pm",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. Mountain of denudation is another term for",
A: "Volcanic mountain.",
B: "Fold mountain.",
C: "glock mountain.",
D: "Residual mountain.",
answer: "D. Residual mountain.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. When the moon occurs in between the Earth and the Sun in a perfect straight line, which of the following eclipse occurs?",
A: "Partial",
B: "Full",
C: "Solar",
D: "Lunar",
answer: "C. Solar",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. Which of the following desert landforms is associated with wind deposition?",
A: "Butte",
B: "Yardang",
C: "Wadi",
D: "Barchan",
answer: "D. Barchan",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. Factors which influence the practice of immigration include all except",
A: "Unreliable rainfall.",
B: "High rainfall.",
C: "Need for more food.",
D: "Need for more food.",
answer: "B. High rainfall.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. Which of the following is a service industry?",
A: "Banking industry",
B: "Food processing plant",
C: "Cement factory",
D: "Pharmaceutical industry",
answer: "A. Banking industry",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. A negative effect of mineral exploitation is",
A: "Afforestation.",
B: "Hydration.",
C: "Pollution.",
D: "Oxidation.",
answer: "C. Pollution.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. The system of agriculture which combines the growing of crops and rearing of animals is known as",
A: "dairy fanning.",
B: "mixed cropping.",
C: "mixed farming..",
D: "shifting cultivation.",
answer: "C. mixed farming.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. Which of the following statements is true of transhumance?",
A: "It is the seasonal migration of animal rearers in mountainous areas.",
B: "It is practised by Europeans.",
C: "It involves the growing of specialized crops.",
D: "It is another name for mixed fttrming.",
answer: "A. It is the seasonal migration of animal rearers in mountainous areas.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. Most rural settlements in developing countries of Africa",
A: "are nucleated.",
B: "are dispersed.",
C: "have dense transport network.",
D: "have satellite towns.",
answer: "B. are dispersed.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. Which of the following environmental resources is non-renewable?",
A: "Rain",
B: "Mineral",
C: "Water",
D: "Oxygen",
answer: "B. Mineral",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. A town which is situated at the meeting point of roads is termed",
A: "Nodal.",
B: "Port.",
C: "Confluence.",
D: "Gap.",
answer: "C. Confluence.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. A major problem of air transportation in developing countries is",
A: "Inadequate passengers.",
B: "Slow speed.",
C: "Inadequate capital.",
D: "Inadequate space for cargo.",
answer: "C. Inadequate capital.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. All these factors determine what a country can produce except",
A: "Size of the country.",
B: "Technology.",
C: "Climate.",
D: "Natural endowment",
answer: "A. Size of the country.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. Which of the following best explains the rapid urban population growth in developing countries of Africa?",
A: "Urban areas have mote medical faciliities.",
B: "Many people migrate to urban areas in search ofjobs.",
C: "Urban areas have more living spaces.",
D: "There is greater security in urban areas.",
answer: "B. Many people migrate to urban areas in search of jobs.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. Which of the following environmental hazards is prevalent in coastal areas?",
A: "Drought",
B: "Deforestation",
C: "Pollution",
D: "Flooding",
answer: "D. Flooding",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. Commodities which are used inworld trade exclude",
A: "Agricultural goods.",
B: "Manufactured goods.",
C: "Mineral resources.",
D: "Human trafficking.",
answer: "D. Human trafficking.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. The Ruhr industrial area in Germany is noted for the production of",
A: "Iron and steel.",
B: "Vehicles.",
C: "Petroleum products.",
D: "Copper and aluminium.",
answer: "A. Iron and steel.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. Which of the following criteria is not important in distinguishing between a village and a town?",
A: "Geographical situation.",
B: "Population size.",
C: "Range of liinctions.",
D: "Variety of activities.",
answer: "A. Geographical situation",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},


]